Guide to the Schlanger Family Papers, 1937-1985 MS 863
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Schlanger Family papers
1937-1985
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Schlanger, Lee
MS 863
.25 Linear Feet 1 box, 1 folder in map drawer
This collection is made up of one box containing correspondence, photographs, news clippings, certificates, newsletters, and programs from the Schlanger Family, spanning from 1937-1985.
Scope and Contents
Certificates, correspondence, news clippings/newsletters, a photograph, a program, and an interview transcript document the lives of members of the Schlanger family and their involvement in the Houston Jewish Community from 1937-1985. Of particular interest is Daniel Schlanger's City of Houston Normal and High School Diploma from 1919. The collection also contains a sealed copy of the Jewish Herald Voice from 1973.
Biographical / Historical
Daniel Schlanger was born in Houston, Texas, on 22 January 1902, to Louis Nathan Schlanger and Hinda Schlanger after emigrating from Germany. He grew up in Houston and, following graduation in May of 1919 from the City of Houston Normal and High School, he attended University of Texas Law School. Daniel practiced law in Houston and was a senior partner at Schlanger, Cook and Cohn. Daniel was very active in the Houston Jewish Community, serving as president of the Jewish Community Center, Southern Region National Jewish Welfare Board, Jewish Community Council, Temple Beth El, and Jewish Home for the Aged.
Rella Greenberg was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on 8 July 1908, to Samuel Charles (S.C.) and Katie Greenberg. Rella's family emigrated from Russia to Pittsburgh, where the family would later own a retail store. The family moved to Texas to pursue the oil business. Daniel and Rella met while Daniel was working as the Greenberg's lawyer. Rella and Daniel married 26 May 1937, at Congregation Beth El in Houston. They had one son, Lee Schlanger, born 4 April 1940.
Daniel Schlanger died on 31 January 1973, and Rella Schlanger died on 28 September 1995. Both are buried at Emanu El Memorial Park.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in five series as follows: Series I: Certificates; Series II: Correspondence; Series III: Newspaper/Newsletters; Series IV: Photographs; Series V: Programs; Series VI: Transcripts
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Lee Schlanger donated the papers in May of 2019.
Index Terms
Subjects
Newspapers; Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
personal correspondence; photographs; certificates; newsletters
Subjects (Persons)
Schlanger, Lee
- Series I: Certificates, 1948-1985
  - Certificate to Daniel Schlanger from Congregation Beth Yeshurun, 1948-02-13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resolution of Appreciation from the Jewish Community Center to Daniel Schlanger, 1953-05-18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Association of Social Workers Certificates to Rella Schlanger, 1955-10-01-1984-03-15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jewish Community Council of Houston Certificate of Merit to Rella Schlanger, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Statue of Liberty Ellis Island Centennial Commission Certificate for Rella Schlanger, c. 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - City of Houston Normal and High School Diploma, Daniel Schlanger, 1919-05-28 (Map-drawer 189, Folder 6)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Jewish Welfare Bureau Flower Fund Announcement (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III: Newspaper/Newsletters, 1937-1984
  - News Clippings, 1937-10-1984-12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Houston Jewish Home for the Aged Bulletins, 1967-01; 1967-06 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dan Schlanger Obituary, Copy of sealed Jewish Herald Voice, 1973-10-08 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series: IV: Photographs, n.d.
  - Photograph of Event with Daniel Schlanger, Rabbi Kahn, and Rabbi Schachtel (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series V: Programs, 1969
  - 26th Anniversary Dinner Program for Jewish Home for the Aged, 1969-02-02 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series VI: Transcripts, 1984-03-22
  - Rella Schlanger Women of Achievement Interview Transcript, 1984-03-22 (Box 1, Folder 12)